<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://muktabh.xyz/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://muktabh.xyz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-23T10:36:25-05:00</updated><id>https://muktabh.xyz/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Muktabh’s Website</title><subtitle>Muktabh's contact and musings</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Views_on_ai_ludditism</title><link href="https://muktabh.xyz/2020/05/23/Views_On_AI_Ludditism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Views_on_ai_ludditism" /><published>2020-05-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://muktabh.xyz/2020/05/23/Views_On_AI_Ludditism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muktabh.xyz/2020/05/23/Views_On_AI_Ludditism.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;some-thoughts-around-the-ai-hysteria-being-created-from-quora-answers&quot;&gt;Some thoughts around the AI hysteria being created [From Quora answers]&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some answers I wrote regarding the AI hysteria that is being created using misinformation, fake news and sensationalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-artificial-intelligence-will-or-may-lead-to-an-unanticipated-crisis-if-it-starts-to-code-itself-how-true-is-it&quot;&gt;My answer to “Artificial intelligence will or may lead to an unanticipated crisis if it starts to code itself? How true is it?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally answered here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/TSC6dR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chill!! People who are asking such questions need to first of all stop worrying and stop reading media articles trying to scare them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are decades (maybe centuries) away from totally automating tasks which require such high level of mental capability. Present Artificial Intelligence can at best approximate tasks which require 2–3 seconds of human decision making that is all. Also most AI we have developed right now is not &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_general_intelligence&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Artificial general intelligence - Wikipedia&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(the one which you watch on movies) but task specific algorithms. We have not even created Terminator/Skynet 0.0.1 yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer your question directly, it might be a problem if AI starts implementing a better AI itself, thus increasing its capability at a superhuman rate making humans obsolete. But this is like hundreds of other low probability doomsday scenarios like an Alien civilization attacking and colonizing us or Earth’s capability to support life getting over. So no point worrying about it in real life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-what-is-deepfake-technology&quot;&gt;My answer to “What is Deepfake technology?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally answered here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/pNnxiL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deepfake is essentially creating fake images/videos/audio/text using Deep Learning techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you remember a recent viral app which used to create images of how a person would look if they were old or applied makeup, the images it was creating were fake images generated by AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the term “Deepfake” is generally used for describing negative usage of such technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you can have someone’s face placed in an objectionable photograph, someone being made to speak fake things they never said in a video and a fake audio in someone’s voice or just a fake news article using Generative Deep Learning algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example there are websites where objectionable videos of celebrities are created by morphing their faces into existing pornography using Deep Learning. There is also danger of a video being made with a politician being made to say something that they have not using such technology to sway the public opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t that such fake photographs or videos or audio cannot be created by humans. They can be and have been created in the past and even now. Just that Deep Learning algorithms bring “automation” to it, that is they can now be created in large quantities without human involvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will put some examples here which you can see and understand how AI can generate video/image/text samples :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generating Videos Using Deep Learning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aliaksandrsiarohin.github.io/first-order-model-website/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;First order model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/AliaksandrSiarohin/first-order-model/master/sup-mat/vox-teaser.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/AliaksandrSiarohin/first-order-model/master/sup-mat/vox-teaser.gif&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generating Images Using Deep Learning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Semi-supervised StyleGAN: Disentanglement is through mutual information loss. Propose new metrics for measuring disentanglement in generator. Take-away: small amount of supervision is enough for disentanglement and high-res generation &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NVIDIAAI?ref_src=twsrc^tfw&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;@NVIDIAAI&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/FDh26WbiQQ&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/FDh26WbiQQ&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— Anima Anandkumar (hiring) (@AnimaAnandkumar) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AnimaAnandkumar/status/1237993418405466112?ref_src=twsrc^tfw&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;March 12, 2020&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/animesh_garg/status/1237756934662623232/photo/1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Animesh Garg on Twitter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generating Text Using Deep Learning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://openai.com/blog/better-language-models/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Better Language Models and Their Implications&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-05-23-Views_On_AI_Ludditism/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-should-we-be-worried-about-deep-fakes-and-the-misuse-of-facial-recognition&quot;&gt;My answer to “Should we be worried about deep fakes and the misuse of facial recognition?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally answered here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/Tx6CUl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the only aspect of Artificial Intelligence that can disrupt our world for a very long time to come is going to be DeepFakes. The reason is not because the technology is itself very harmful, the reason is because humans are emotional and don’t really put a thought before believing and sharing videos or voice messages. You could basically generate photos , videos and voice clips of a person doing/saying whatever you want using these techniques. I will not be surprised if fake media created by these technology be used to instigate violence or bad faith. In a world where fake news is widespread and fake news busters can spread fake news too, it is going to be big challenge to tackle Deepfakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The misuse of facial recognition is actually somewhat fearmongering and luddism. It probably makes the world somewhat less private, but every technology since the invention of cameras has done so for a very long time and its a continuing trend since years. I think the probability of using Face Recognition for bad purposes is not that high. That said, I think there are already regulations in place in various countries to make sure Facial Recognition cannot be used to harm people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-why-deep-mind-ai-of-google-failed-to-answer-1111111&quot;&gt;My answer to “Why Deep mind AI of Google failed to answer 1+1+1+1+1+1+1?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally answered here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://qr.ae/pNnedF&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/pNnedF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many assumptions in the question appear wrong:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Deepmind is a company, its not an AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The way you refer to AI, it feels like you are talking about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_general_intelligence&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Artificial general intelligence – Wikipedia&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Most AI we have in the world (and most of what Deepmind builds) is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weak_AI&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Weak AI - Wikipedia&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;!-- end list --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;AGI (Artificial General Intelligence) is a theoretical future where computers can learn any new task when presented to them like humans, is decades if not centuries away. Weak AI means a Computer needs to be programmed to perform one task, like detecting cavity in teeth or playing Atari games.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- end list --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Weak AI variant for problems like “1 + 1 + 1 … “ exists. That is simple mathematical expression parsing and evaluation. What Deepmind was trying to do was to use a Weak AI model generally used to look for features in language (LSTMs are the algorithm) to solve mathematical problems. All it tells is Weak AI algorithms to extract features on Natural Language cannot learn to solve Mathematical problem as of now.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- end list --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Please don’t read pop sci articles on AI like these: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techtimes.com/articles/241193/20190410/googles-deepmind-failed-a-high-school-level-math-test-what-does-this-mean.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Google’s DeepMind Failed A High School Level Math Test: What Does This Mean?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; . They are just not informative enough and misguide.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-what-you-think-about-data-scientists-automated-and-unemployed-by-2025-article&quot;&gt;My answer to “What you think about “Data Scientists Automated and Unemployed by 2025?” article?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link to original answer : &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/What-you-think-about-Data-Scientists-Automated-and-Unemployed-by-2025-article/answers/16871059&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://www.quora.com/What-you-think-about-Data-Scientists-Automated-and-Unemployed-by-2025-article/answers/16871059&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The so called Data Scientists who use off the shelf Machine Learning algorithms on simple data WILL be automated pretty soon, infact Amazon/Azure/Google ML services already do so. To be frank, calling sklearn.fit_predict with different parameters is not really hard and is kind of repetitive.&lt;br /&gt;
The real world is slightly different, A lot of real world Data Scientists are actually Data Mungers, who clean/transform the data (which is really hard to automate), and then Hyperparameter adjusters who apply black box algorithms on top of it (which is easy to automate).&lt;br /&gt;
Other easy repetitive tasks, which involve simple repetitive work and involve humans for the hack of it (say Data Entry Operators, Customer Support chat people, ) are being automated at a steep rate too. Surprisingly, some aspects of art (some form of painting, music, lyrics writing) is being automated too, which I thought was impossible to.&lt;br /&gt;
The day to day tasks of actual Data Scientists, say working at Facebook AI research and Google Brain (writing different Artificial Intelligence agents) will be one of the last to be automated, as it is generally very hard. So I think they will be one of the last in last in the  line of losing “survival of the fittest” battle to Machines. A time when Machine can deduce algorithms is still far off in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-what-will-be-the-need-for-humans-if-we-automate-everything-with-machine-learning-and-robotics-what-will-humans-do-in-the-future&quot;&gt;My answer to “What will be the need for humans if we automate everything with machine learning and robotics? What will humans do in the future?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link to original answer here: &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://www.quora.com/What-will-be-the-need-for-humans-if-we-automate-everything-with-machine-learning-and-robotics-What-will-humans-do-in-the-future/answer/Muktabh-Mayank&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it necessary for humans to work ? Do any other species of plants and animals work jobs ? Don’t other species live ? Is the only purpose of human existence to make Excel and Powerpoint sheets or write Python code ? These are deep metaphysical questions which are more philosophical and have no real (only theoretical ) answers. Also this is not my answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more practical answer is that automation has always been coming, jobs have always been automated. Shoe Makers were automated by factories and chariot drivers and horse tamers were automated by cars. What always happens is new jobs were created every time (factory workers, car drivers) requiring lesser number of humans, so that humans could engage in more intellectually demanding fields. The same is happening now, with incoming AI technology, jobs are changing. The difference is that while it took generations earlier for a change to reflect, people will see drastic changes in their lifetime (that’s probably the only challenge I see, people will not really be able to “settle” on a career for all their lives pretty soon and will require to learn-unlearn many times in their lifetime) . &lt;strong&gt;The (wrongful) fear is because we see only one aspect of it, not the other side. AI does automate stuff, but sum of human achievements is not a Zero Sum game, it will grow larger.&lt;/strong&gt; While you might not be required to enter data in Excel (one random example) searching web due to AI, a bigger intellectual challenge can be taken over by same person than Excel data entry (like say solving Cancer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-will-data-science-and-machine-learning-get-automated-leading-to-lesser-opportunities-for-data-scientists&quot;&gt;My answer to “Will data science and machine learning get automated leading to lesser opportunities for data scientists”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally answered here: &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://www.quora.com/Will-data-science-and-machine-learning-get-automated-leading-to-lesser-opportunities-for-data-scientists-as-per-https-www-datasciencecentral-com-profiles-blogs-data-scientists-automated-and-unemployed-by-2025-update/answer/Muktabh-Mayank&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. (2025 is not the date I think its going to happen, but its inevitable and will happen in near future). They will be to a good extent. So will be Software Developers, designers, manual workers, teachers, linguists, musicians, game developers etc,etc. There are already rudimentary projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.floydhub.com/turning-design-mockups-into-code-with-deep-learning/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Turning Design Mockups Into Code With Deep Learning&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which can turn a design mockup into HTML/CSS code, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/carpedm20/ENAS-pytorch&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;carpedm20/ENAS-pytorch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which can design neural networks without a Data Scientist, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/janakirammsv/2018/04/15/why-automl-is-set-to-become-the-future-of-artificial-intelligence/#5bfa74e0780a&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Why AutoML Is Set To Become The Future Of Artificial Intelligence&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , system which can generate new characters for games, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.business-standard.com/article/international/microsoft-ai-can-translate-chinese-to-english-just-as-accurately-as-humans-118031500414_1.html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Microsoft AI can translate Chinese to English just as accurately as humans&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.computing.co.uk/ctg/news/3028065/baidus-deep-voice-can-clone-speech-with-less-than-four-seconds-of-training&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Baidu’s Deep Voice can clone speech with less than four seconds of training | Computing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and multiple such projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OpanAI’s new project can generate programs given specs : &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=utuz7wBGjKM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-05-23-Views_On_AI_Ludditism/media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the artificially drawn faces by latest GANs , designers will find it harder to compete with the new quality. &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://youtu.be/XOxxPcy5Gr4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-05-23-Views_On_AI_Ludditism/media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI will impact every job profile which exists as of now, Data Scientists no exception, automating some or a lot of work people spend their time on. For a lot of time these systems will become a &amp;lt;Man + Machine&amp;gt; AI systems rather than just a Human working before stuff is totally automated. So its not like everyone becomes redundant day 1, but they will eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full Automation of any field is going to take way longer than 2025 IMHO. That said, yes a lot less people will be needed for the same task as of today. Then what will people do you ask ? newer more complex tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automation is not a new phenomenon. Think about the railway breaks a long time back: &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://youtu.be/EEUkmP2nyxo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-05-23-Views_On_AI_Ludditism/media/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much work was once needed to just stop the train. A lot lesser work is needed today to run/stop the train and not just that, slowly trains are moving towards full automation, but right now they are in a &amp;lt;man + machine&amp;gt; stage. A lot of jobs will stay in this phase for sometime before full automation kicks in. But unlike railways, which take generations to move from one stage of automation to another, AI is causing changes at a phase at a very high rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the effect on a general Data Scientist (or any white/blue collared worker for that matter):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Adapt to AI. Automation has started, but AI aided jobs will stay for a few more years than non-AI jobs. So while no plain X jobs by 2025, X + AI jobs might be around till 2030.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Things wont be like earlier generations where one skill learnt gets you a job for entire life. One needs to be open to learning new skills and get started in the middle of life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Average level of education needed will be high. Think of it, 50 years back “High School” was all the education needed for most jobs. Now its somewhere between high school and graduation. Masters and Research might look like the next frontier, but these degrees are too slow and broad. Coursera like courses will become more important in catching new skillsets. You might already see people doing that a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;With more uncertainty in jobs, millenials probably will want to be a less “spend-y” and more frugal. You can see things happening already &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.in/6-reasons-why-more-millennials-arent-buying-homes/articleshow/59005530.cms&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;6 reasons why more millennials aren’t buying homes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and will actually increase. AI is just a trend in a longer cycle of Automation and millenials are at a point in history where education+society was according to old norms but automation has reached a point where jobs have become uncertain. Younger people will be smarter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Some thoughts around the AI hysteria being created [From Quora answers]</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Views On Indian Startups</title><link href="https://muktabh.xyz/2020/04/14/Views-on-Indian-Startups.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Views On Indian Startups" /><published>2020-04-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-04-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://muktabh.xyz/2020/04/14/Views-on-Indian-Startups</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muktabh.xyz/2020/04/14/Views-on-Indian-Startups.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;some-thoughts-about-indian-startup-scene-as-various-answers-to-quora-questions&quot;&gt;Some Thoughts about Indian Startup Scene (As various answers to Quora questions)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-how-can-you-define-the-indian-startup-economy&quot;&gt;My answer to “How can you define the Indian startup economy?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally Answered Here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/TDM7li&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is in a unique position demographically and economically to create many different types of companies. This demographic dividend of youth creates unique opportunities :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;India’s cost of living is low, so you can still get relatively better talent at a certain wage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;India’s population is growing and many people are entering into the workforce. Given these people are trained well, a supply-demand gap will not arise for certain time period and hence wages will remain relatively stable for a long time time to come. This makes sure doing more and more innovation doesn’t get costlier.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Indian government is no longer a Soviet style planned, capitalists-are-pig preaching economy. Same with people, people no longer wanted to work in stagnant government jobs where hard work had no rewards and the most optimal behavior was to work just enough to not get into trouble, but rather to make money with hard work and enjoy their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;That said, a lot of these people will start getting good wages making a larger middle class. This creates a larger market where you can sell goods and services making more people get good wages and increasing the market even more.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a great opportunity, with a window between years 1990–2050.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While initially we let large companies come to India and use India as a talent pool (and market) for a very long time (when I completed my engineering in 2012 at BITS Pilani, working for a large multinational was the top choice, most of my batchmates work for a multinational in India or abroad), giving employment to a certain number of people creating a primary new middle class, we cannot hope to sustain our growing population with these multinationals who bring only selected jobs here. The first middle class we created with this capitalist boom of 1990s and 2000s also created a stronger demand (market) for goods and services and created a talent pool. This can do wonders .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what happened when there was no startup economy in India. A very good period to think about this was the 2000s. We already had a middle class who believed in neoliberalism/globalism very strongly and we were using American products like there is no tomorrow. Think of it, no big search engines, social networks, Electronic manifactures and Mobile OS came out of India, None. We were really happy using Symbian, Orkut, Facebook and others. Think of the amount of technical expertise and talent pool these companies would have created if India had its own Baidu, Yandex, Android or Xiaomi. This would have created way more startups and jobs and market than what we have right now. &lt;em&gt;We missed out !&lt;/em&gt; Governments did not have confidence to put policies in place which could help benefit our ecosystem or they maybe did not realize the power of ecosystems and economies of scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian Entrepreneurs of 2000s and early 2010s had to prove their mettle by sweat and blood. They proved that companies could be built in India, large ones. Zoho, Infoedge, Freshworks, Flipkart, PayTM, SnapDeal and startups of that generation deserve respect just for standing up and building up a company. That is what gave confidence to government that Indians can build large companies and confidence of next generation of entrepreneurs that its possible to make it big with some risks and made people believe they can spend money on an Indian website or app. The fellows and contemporaries of these entrepreneurs who saw their success came back from their high paid multinational jobs to join the startup ecosystem and the story began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When we serve our own market, we create an ecosystem:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let’s see what happened when we have an startup ecosystem (my preferred term instead of startup economy). Any technology trend has 3 steps -&amp;gt; 1. Early Developments , 2. Growth and 3. Consolidation. With our startup system maturing, we still haven’t reached the level of doing Early Developments of technology trends (say food tech, coworking, ride hailing, O2O etc did not start in India but still in US and China), but already at growth stage we can build companies which can cater to our markets specifically. This adds new bigger startups to our ecosystem all the time. These bring in new talent that is economically powerful that can drive the next wave building even larger startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In first wave of startups like Search Engines and Social Networks we were so behind that had no Indian companies, in the next wave like ride hailing and e-commerce, we had an Indian counterpart racing with a foreign high-growth startup from outside (Flipart/OLA) and in the next step, we have all Indian companies in fintech and hotel space and foodtech (Oyo / PayTM / Swiggy and Zomato/ so many lending startups).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have not mentioned, we are progressing very fast in not a very long duration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How this contributes to building better ecosystem ? While operational jobs will always be in India for an Indian and Foreign company, that is foreigners will seldom deliver food in India, high worth and innovative jobs come to India with Indian companies. For example, way higher ratio of product managers of an Indian startup will sit in India than product managers of Foreign startups. This adds way more to ecosystem as for the next innovation India will be more prepared and maybe Indian ecosystem is so early to some technology trend that we have our own google in that space. The other thing is that these high innovative individuals earn much more and create a more powerful market than just operational people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also see the progress in technology development too. I consider Infosys to be the first successful Indian startup in software. From primarily deploying software as to how old software companies of India worked to making cheaper variants of successful software products, I think we are soon going to see the next break through where Indian Software startups which dominate by their innovation will emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innovation follows large businesses and ecosystem that can invest in them:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once there is demand and market (people willing to adapt and government not-interfering or better helping) and supply (a talent pool that can build services that can cater to demand), economics happens. In 2000s, There was high respect of “multinationals” in India and people wanted to buy/use their products, this created a huge market for multinational corporations in India and frankly, they are monopolies in India, even bigger market shares than in their own companies. Think about Google, Facebook, Suzuki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, look at the long term repercussions. I will talk about software because I know the space well. India still doesn’t know widely how to build Server Farms, hugely scalable software tools (have you heard of an Indian mapreduce ? an Indian Golang ? Indian Tensorflow ?), despite giving an opportunity to scale these companies so much. These companies now have so much edge that probably any Indian Search Engine / Social Media innovation at best will be a copy and be months if not years behind in tech due to lack of ecosystem. A lot of these tools have their parallel in China and Russia which have their own ecosystems. Not saying that using non-tensorflow is a must, but knowledge of building tensorflow-like failed software also helps drive next step of innovation. That knowledge needs to stay in ecosystem. India had no ecosystem, so no one stayed back which created a bad image and lead to further brain drain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High innovation thing like say building a Tensorflow requires a very very strong pre-existing business that can take load of R\&amp;amp;D on top of their nominal business. Only old very successful companies can do it. They will hence create an advantage which is very strong and that cannot be taken away from them. Moat is the terms startups have for it. Tensorflow innovations will slowly make companies using the tool migrate to Google cloud just by the features. This is going to be a big business for Google in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our companies will be able to do it locally after they grow really big and are able to attract our top talent to stay and in fact bring top talent from outside. Again, all this top talent, will be very highly paid and will spend their money in the country, making our economy bigger. Operational jobs are never going anywhere too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why some people don’t like startup risks and prefer the older “safer” way :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I observed this trend in other answer to the question and thus am adding this heading which is not really relevant to the question)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well because the old multinational way, a few people of India got employment in large stable multi national companies which were expanding. A small set of relatively safer jobs were created. A company in early phases of a technology trend has more jobs, but these are more volatile. So a section of people who would have the advantage of the safer jobs of multinational might not like more volumes of higher-uncertainty jobs getting created. We have to leave this Soviet style mentality behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-why-are-huge-indian-tech-startups-bleeding-losses&quot;&gt;My answer to “Why are huge Indian tech startups bleeding losses?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally Answered Here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/TleOX5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because they are not meant to make profits in their initial days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian media (and self anointed experts most people listen to) is quite old fashioned about running a company and still tries to put everything in perspective of the 1990s, the world has moved beyond that to what I now call the “Amazon model”. Other companies which have similar approaches are FaceBook, Uber, Turo, AirBnB, (Indian startups which you are probably talking about in question -&amp;gt; ) Oyo, Swiggy, Zomato and so on. “Smart” answers like “they are not innovative enough” I see here have to understand some of the world’s largest companies have been formed with this strategy. All these startups (not all startups btw, many have different routes to growth) are following is a well formed strategy successful companies have used. Investors have put their money for exactly the same purpose in these companies : burn and grow big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These companies will invest for a very long time to build a platform first, will come up with a large set of users and then this economy of scale helps them build many products and solutions they can monetize to invest again in growth, this is going to be a cycle till the company keeps growing fast in valuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for example, Amazon was building e-commerce, then build a scalable could service to scale it up and then built AWS which they now monetize. Similarly Ola build a ride hailing service, then built a wallet to pay for that service, then will use that wallet to get into fintech and so on do forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to understand that investors have not put money into these companies for dividends on profit but growth in valuation of their equity and they are actually all growing rich by burning the money. They are doing exactly what their investors have put their money in for. This is not a sign of weakness or being unstable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are working at such a startup company where they show consistent losses and you are not sure how to differentiate between whether its a good company or not , find out information about “How fast is the valuation of company growing ?”. If the valuation is growing fast and well, the company is working as expected, there is no problem !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-why-do-90-of-startups-fail-in-india&quot;&gt;My answer to “Why do 90% of startups fail in India?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally Answered here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/TVQM9c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;90% startups fail EVERYWHERE. There is nothing special (or worse) about India in terms of startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Startups fail because of following reasons most of time :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Working on a business idea which founders cannot convince others about (investors to invest in idea/ customers to buy a product/ users to use a product).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Start scaling and spending before Product Market Fit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Disagreements between founders.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Not being to deliver what they promise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be many many possible reasons why startups fail, everything needs to go right for a startup to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-can-a-startup-become-successful-by-outsourcing-100-of-its-employees&quot;&gt;My answer to “Can a startup become successful by outsourcing 100% of its employees?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally answered here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/Tlev1W&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from giving out very small non-repetition tasks, I personally don’t think a startup should outsource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible things you can outsource (with good IP agreements) :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Designing websites and logo.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Writing one time programming modules like say one specific task for one specific client which your product team won’t have to work on.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Headhunting for specific profiles, organizing hackathons etc. Things that you know require lot of work for very short periods of time and then get done. Headhunting I am yet not 100% sure, in the long run, your inhouse HR team needs to build capability to find the type of people you need and essentially you are not letting that capability build.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Office maintenance, accounts, lawyers etc. These things will not build company competencies if done in-house and are costlier in-house too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Some content writing can be outsourced but this is a tricky one as someone from outside your company who can write an article which is good from point of view of your company is hard to find.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lead Generation might be outsourced after you have a very good idea of your customer.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Anything can be outsourced early in startup by the time you are building a in-house team for the purpose, but as founders , its one’s responsibility to get the team in place as fast as possible for any task apart from ones listed in 1–6. The outsourcing companies that drop you regular mails do so because they assume you are a very young startup (or a service company where price cutting is a goal). Points 1–6 are often needed at a very early stage of a startup as well, but can extend too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you should never outsource:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Technology: Technology is your moat, if you outsource that, what competency does your team have.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Digital Marketing : If you are B2B SaaS, you need to come up with your own digital media marketing strategy to beat or equal asymmetrically large opponents. If you outsource this, how would cookie cutter templates help you equal large and established brands who apply cookie cutter templates too.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Product Design and Management : Same reason as 1.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will add to list as I come up with more ideas. HTH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-is-there-actually-a-market-for-deep-tech-startups-in-india&quot;&gt;My answer to “Is there actually a market for Deep Tech startups in India?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally Answered here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://qr.ae/pNnZNf&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/pNnZNf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covering the whole Deep Tech scene in India in one answer would be a bit too much. Couple of chatbots startups are doing OK with Indian banks, do you count chatbots in Deep Tech ? Does acquisition by larger consumer companies count as success (People have made good money there) ? Is the startup building an India specific product or a global product with India as one of its markets?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some general points I would like to make (running a B2B AI startup &lt;a href=&quot;https://paralleldots.xyz/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;ParallelDots&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;catering to clients in India and abroad):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We don’t have enough datapoints to determine if there is a market:&lt;/strong&gt; Deep Tech startups need very good technology and a lot of R\&amp;amp;D. This increases the number of open ends to 2 in B2C (both R\&amp;amp;D and product as opposed to only product in non deep-tech startups) and 3 in B2B (R\&amp;amp;D on top of product and integration). &amp;lt;This no way means B2C is easy, its harder in fact&amp;gt;. Indians (both investors and entrepreneurs) often want the easy way out. So a lot of good engineers will want to work with Google’s of the world, entrepreneurs will try to keep lesser open ends in business and Indian investors will invest in much safer ideas. Many Indian startups are direct copies of successful products from US and China. There is much more probability of these working out. My point is there are too many low hanging fruits opposed to trying a Deep tech startup, so not a lot of people get into deep tech. Less people getting into deep tech means less ideas being tried and less visible success giving rise to (somewhat gloomy) questions like “Is there actually a market for Deep Tech startups in India?” . One answer is “we don’t have enough datapoints to determine if there is a market”. This means no ecosystem, no learning material, so learning-the-hard-way for early bird deep tech startups. “Learning the hard way” is a slow multiple-pivot process too. So more open ends added.&lt;br /&gt;
PS: In no way I blame the Indian psych for this. Life for Indians has sparser rewards than west and they thus are risk averse. Things are getting better and we will see more Deep Tech startups here. Thinking of 11 years back when I joined engineering, there were hardly any startups at all and standard criteria for success was getting a high paying job in US. I think with more success in startup world, we will see successful people (who have had positive reinforcements from previous successes) betting on riskier ideas, some of them getting even more successful. I think the order will be marketplaces -&amp;gt; money transactions -&amp;gt; R\&amp;amp;D heavy software -&amp;gt; R\&amp;amp;D heavy hardware startups. There is a reason the one-percenters are born in an entrepreneurial society.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Its hard to discover a deeptech B2C angle (not just in India):&lt;/strong&gt; There are very few Deep Tech consumer ideas from day 1 in the world. Among FAANG (Apple is a hardware company primarily) only Google was a deeptech consumer software from day 1. Adobe/Microsoft atleast initially were between B2B and B2C. Netflix, Amazon and Facebook have R\&amp;amp;D facilities to enhance their product. Same with Uber, Lyft and Airbnb. Successful consumer ideas which can create a network effect are hard to come by and one which uses Deep Tech is even harder (no wonder so few discovered yet). The existing consumer apps evolve into better versions using deep tech creating a railroad like monopoly &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs.stanford.edu/people/eroberts/cs181/projects/1995-96/corporate-monopolies/development_rrmon.html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Development of the Railroad Monopoly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;!-- end list --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;. DeepTech startups have been acquired by consumer businesses in AI field (in India by Flipkart, Reliance Jio and others) and that is where they will get into usage for vernacular language understanding. I dont know about any AI from day 1 consumer business doing well as of now anywhere in the world. What if Facebook comes up with a blockchain platform in near future ? It will become a monster. Trying to get so many people onboard in a new blockchain startup in India for payments, voting or referendums will be insane, for facebook, its one feature away.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- end list --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In B2B, Indians pay less&lt;/strong&gt;: The same point again, our economy had almost collapsed 30 years back and we have come upto this point absolutely from nothing. Our enterprises are also becoming bigger, but we are still not like US or China say. Just like consumer startups which are gradually solving more and more high ended problems, enterprises are also only recently waking up to potential of DeepTech. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/topic/ParallelDots&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;ParallelDots&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a B2B business and this is a sector where we see potential in India already. We have been able to sell 30,000 - 200,000 $/year licenses in India for AI software. We have sold similar cost licenses to US companies too, but if we divide the license cost we sell by the market cap of company we sell to, US is ahead. That said, one time customer acquisition cost in India is way lower. India is also more comfortable to sell in(because its home). So both markets have tradeoffs. &lt;strong&gt;I will from my current learning say, building a B2B deeptech product only for India probably wont make sense, but building it for world and selling it in India as well seems doable.&lt;/strong&gt; We are still working out things, but we believe we are closer to make ParallelDots a success.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- end list --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Some other hypothesis we have from our experience in deep tech B2B as of now (please take this as a gain of salt as this is all anecdotal and we are still not exactly the most successful startup out there):&lt;br /&gt;
* Dont sell to startups&lt;br /&gt;
* Avoid other B2B companies as first clients, they might either try to acquire IP or might rather create a competitor than try you out. Just saying they shouldn’t be early customers, you can sell established products to them.&lt;br /&gt;
* Dont build a tool for technology company (esp in AI). &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/thelaunchpad/your-deep-learning-tools-for-enterprises-startup-will-fail-94fb70683834&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Your Deep-Learning-Tools-for-Enterprises Startup Will Fail&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
* Make sure your investor is aligned with you and doesn’t get impatient. Also having a long runway is important.&lt;br /&gt;
* Try (tech savvy + smart) people as early adopters. They know about technology and will be willing to adopt. Just tech savvy people who are not smart will guide you with wrong/irrelevant use cases, smart but non tech-savvy people might not find your technology relevant. In India, a easy proxy is to search for engineers from IITs etc. at a good level in enterprises. Early adopters are very important. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/growth.html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Startup = Growth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
* Stay away from (non-investing) accelerators, (free/paid but not in equity) advisors and startup schools and focus on product market fit and growth.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure if this answers the question exactly (because as I said earlier, it is a really broad question and there are not enough datapoints to come to conclusions), but it might lead to a good conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: There is of course a huge market for Deep Tech service companies in India. Most of our big software companies are actually service companies and we will have in the near future an “Infosys in AI” from India. I am not talking about them as I dont count them as startups. Its a different type of business with different constraints than what you have here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-what-is-the-future-of-machine-learningdeep-learning-startups&quot;&gt;My answer to “What is the future of machine learning/deep learning startups?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally answered here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/TZQf4r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally believe startups should be judged as just that : startups. The future of Machine Learning / Deep Learning startups will depend on how successful they are as a startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A startup is a business that :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Has Product Market Fit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The market of the PMF (point 1) is large enough&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Has a good growth curve MoM or YoY in terms of revenue or usage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Can scale the growth with application of more capital.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is nothing different a Machine Learning/Deep Learning startup needs to do than the above 4 points. If they are successful at developing a PMF, showing good growth and raising good capital, they will work well. This was true in past, is true now and will be true in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Machine Learning/ Deep Learning in a startup increases the risks by a bit (that you have to develop these algorithms) but also functions as a moat in some way. Just building the product itself creates some barrier to entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now come the hype part. Whenever a new technology pops up, be it Deep Learning, Cryptocurrencies, blockchains etc., you will see a lot of money going into the sector. This creates a supply-demand dis-balance and the money can hence take more risk. This is what a bubble is and a lot of startups which are beyond the real metrics (that is the 4 above) get funded in this bubble. We had a bubble like this in Deep Learning startups too. So for example a startup which “makes a free and open source Deep Learning framework in Haskell” might even get funded in this type of an era. “makes a free and open source Deep Learning framework in Haskell” is an example where there is low usage (few data scientists use Haskell, which is a programming language most useful for programming language research) and is still free and open source (no monetization plan). For sure , Deep Learning startups have crossed this hype age and you can see consolidation, as mentioned in the other answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-what-are-the-key-factors-that-influence-a-startups-success-using-an-ai-technology&quot;&gt;My answer to “What are the key factors that influence a startup’s success using an AI technology?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally answered here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/pNnx9y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the following points are marker of a successful AI startup:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Has it got early users ? If it is slightly mature, Has it got a Product Market Fit and has it started generating recurring revenues ? This is pretty similar to what one would expect of any B2B startup.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Have they been able to setup what we at ParallelDots call “Data Operations Pipeline” ? You need an efficient method to create initial and ongoing supervised training data for AI algorithms ? This is something really important and unless gets sorted, the tech will be lackluster. An AI startup with lackluster tech is meh. Although we might expect Data Scientists to do wonders, they are really nothing without “Data” they can work on. A good metric to evaluate is to check how much annotated training data the startup has.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Intellectual Property and AI talent: Apart from the network effect in business and data collection, which a business can achieve only after it grows big, the only moat a young startup can create is by their intellectual property and getting good AI talent efficiently. These are things which are slightly hard to judge by non-tech people as a lot of open source and second grade talent can be marketed really well. Good metric to evaluate is publications/ open source contributions and Kaggle scores.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Some other things to keep in mind are:&lt;br /&gt;
A. Current day AI generally cannot predict social outcome. (So you cannot tell if someone’s going to be selected for a job interview or guessing someone’s income from their face). It cannot detect weighty subjective opinionated things like fake news (it can recognize some very pattern based instances of fake news though, like heading basically misleading as compared to article). A good rule of thumb is AI can automatically do what you can do within 3 seconds of looking at a datapoint (photo, sentence, excel row etc). &lt;a href=&quot;https://boingboing.net/2019/11/21/debullshitifying-ai.html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;How to recognize AI snake oil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B. Paid developer tooling is generally a bad idea. (because all paid AI tooling is basically developer tooling). &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/thelaunchpad/your-deep-learning-tools-for-enterprises-startup-will-fail-94fb70683834&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Your Deep-Learning-Tools-for-Enterprises Startup Will Fail&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;C. Google/Amazon/Microsoft will eventually offer AI algorithms which can be used across different companies with no change. For other companies to make dent, they have to work into something that is customized for different countries. For example if you just extract out all faces from images, the behemoths will eventually build an algorithm better than yours. However, training an algorithm to recognize company’s own employees, that is hard to build as a generic service. There are some exceptions to this point like China’s Megvii.&lt;br /&gt;
D. If you want to enter healthcare AI and it seems your product needs a government approval (like FDA say), it is a lot of work and founders need to have some expertise or hire some.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- end list --&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Basically one more point of the above is that AI startups need to have multiple expertise (Tech, AI, Business Development, Operations to collect data and client service). Its a relatively new industry and either you should be able to build a team with the expertise such diverse, and/or founders should be capable of getting out of their comfort zone to build new expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-how-is-the-ai-community-shaping-up-in-india-&quot;&gt;My answer to “How is the AI community shaping up in India ?”&lt;/h3&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally Answered here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/Teyr1U&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see a lot of blanket answers here like :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Most AI startups are farce.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;They don’t have Prodduct Market Fit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;They don’t have resources.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because of lack of information. There is no doubt that there is a lot of hype but there are genuine AI first companies in India. If you don’t know about it, please don’t bundle them with the pretentious people you so hate. Hype startups is not a unique phenomenon to India and is very common in Silicon Valley. When a lot of probability of success is dependence upon “impressing” VCs to raise money, you cannot always blame entrepreneurs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.computing.co.uk/ctg/news/3084079/ai-snake-oil&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Much of what’s being sold as ‘AI’ today is snake oil, says Princeton professor | Computing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-04-14-Views-on-Indian-Startups/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a lot of problems in the real world can be solved with simpler technology and you really don’t need AI in everything. Making a startup a success is a hard thing (like really hard). Now you add to it the complexities that come with a AI startup (getting money to buy resources to support the technology and getting a team which can solve the problem statement and startups are expected to grow like crazy while AI research you do is kind of slow), you are basically talking about a way harder to succeed startup. Basically if your odds of succeeding in a startup is 1:100 , succeeding in a AI startup is say 1:500. So the ratio of successful people to pretentious people in AI startup communities is skewed towards the latter (given pretentious people are roughly in the same probability in every sector). I dont blame you too much for generalization, the world does look like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, startups who have a different product and are selling a small AI feature will boast about it a lot because they have invested in it to create a differentiator, but they are neither AI startups, nor you should judge AI first startups according to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I would like to say is that there are startups there which have achieved Product Market Fit of a AI first product , have original technology and research and have raised enough money to have a research team and infrastructure to build technology. We will see some of them become success stories in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some which I can guess with reasonable confidence which do actual AI work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.manthan.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;AI and Analytics Solutions for Consumer Businesses&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://locus.sh/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Logistics Planning, Automation &amp;amp; Optimization | Supply Chain Optimization Software | Locus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://qure.ai/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Artificial Intelligence for Radiology&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://prediblehealth.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Predible Health&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.niramai.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;A Novel Breast Cancer Screening Solution&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sigtuple.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;SigTuple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.silversparro.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;AI powered Video Analytics for Business - Silversparro | Gurugram&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.staqu.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Staqu - Perceiving the future&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paralleldots.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;ParallelDots&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , my own startup. We raised a round of USD 2 Million a few years back and have a rapidly rising Annual Recurring Revenue. We tried out many many products but finally could get a product market fit using our &lt;strong&gt;Computer Vision on retail shelves product.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;. We do research work ourselves and all our AI technology has been developed in house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope I could show that its not all stupidity here in Indian AI startup scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-views-on-startups-disrupting-local-businesses-in-answer-to-are-technology-startups-ruining-indias-economy-&quot;&gt;My views on startups disrupting local businesses in answer to “Are technology startups ruining India’s economy ?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally Answered here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://qr.ae/pNnZGd&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/pNnZGd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait.. what ? In no economics book/report will you see such a thing happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general fear from a “Technology Startup” ruining or distorting a traditional business is just &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Chinese_Stories/The_frog_of_the_well&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Chinese Stories/The frog of the well&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;type situation. (I hope that is the hypothesis on which this question was asked, I cannot think of another reason why this question will be framed). The world is becoming more centralized, connected and institutionalized. Technology Startups are essentially doing the same thing in India. With the new technology tools available (specifically internet and smartphones), they are making the economy more lean, efficient and competitive and addressing a way larger market making things accessible for consumers using network effect. This might come as a surprise(hence this type of questions) to people only aware of old school businesses who are accustomed to more easier times of smaller markets. India cannot get stuck in the rut of status quo of old days and wait for a rude shock, we have to move with the world, maybe even faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand more, there are two types of businesses: arbitrage based (an example is taxi hailing services, retail distributor, or a house broker or any such middleman) and Products and Services (a car producing company, a hairdresser, moviemaker etc). A subset of both types of businesses (and specially middleman businesses) exist just because there is an inefficiency in the market. A lot of inefficient Product and Services businesses went out of existence as middlemen slowly connected people to good product/service providers and the bad ones simply vanished. Think of it, a bakery in your area was slowly replaced by cheaper and better product of a bakery which became the most known bakery in the town and then state and country level bakeries slowly formed. So “Middlemen” businesses in fact emerged to solve inefficient “Product and Services” businesses. Most of small businesses in India slowly migrated to Middlemen businesses from product and services businesses. So a television store in your town just does that, buys TV at INR X and sells it at INR (X + Profit). Middleman instead of trying to produce a television.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now with Internet and Technology, these middlemen are now being optimized one level more. Many layers of inefficient middlemen can now be replaced by a larger company. That is what is happening when Tech startups come up. Its basically the next and modern version of your local singer losing business to Arijeet Singh because ways to transfer good songs over long distance with popularity of audio cassette in 1980s. Ola is replacing your Taxi services, Oyo your typical hotel guy on railway station, Flipkart is replacing your electronic stores and Grofers your grocer shop. They do it at a scale way larger and way more efficient. To win trust, they use cashbacks and discounts instead of their local reputation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-what-initiatives-should-india-take-to-be-an-ai-superpower&quot;&gt;My Answer to “What initiatives should India take to be an AI superpower?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Original Answer Here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/TeyruI&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some advantages in India :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lot of young people. Even if 1% of software engineers in india can be good at AI, we have the largest AI workforce of the world. Similarly, too many entrepreneurs as well.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lot of people interested in working in STEM and esp AI.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Jugaad, art of getting things done with some quirk and meager resources is common.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some disadvantages of India:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Youth not attached to country, often aim of many is to settle outside.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;1 can still be offsetted by our large population, but then, there is too much of a “participation/entitlement culture” . &lt;strong&gt;Because we are Indian citizens, we should have easy education&lt;/strong&gt; (we should have easy access to education, not easy education itself. Most Indian education system is “navigable”, its hard, but we all know there is a way to somehow get through it without putting the work required. Last years’ papers, teacher coachings, getting class notes and other shortcuts. Most students, even the ones who top, will understand what I am saying, they all know there is a way where they could have studied better.). &lt;strong&gt;When we get easy education, we want easy jobs.&lt;/strong&gt; Easy jobs are serfdom, modern serfdom is not as hard as earlier and lot of people want to get stuck there and enjoy life. No “superpower” can come out of serfdom, AI superpower, defence superpower whatever. &lt;strong&gt;Discouraging risk taking has to go from our culture. Fear of failing makes our education, jobs, research institutes , universities, companies look for easy hacks out.&lt;/strong&gt; “Jugaad” (at which Indians are really smart) is a very very good thing if it achieves an objective different from doing-less-work, unfortunately, Indians tend to use Jugaad for this a lot. You all know about the student who scores really well while there is someone else better at the subject, or a famous software engineer who seldom codes and mostly writes Medium blogs.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Innovators coming out of our engineering education/jobs/research institutes is exception, not norm, because people figure out shortcuts. You cannot innovate if you are not well educated/avoid hardwork about a topic.&lt;br /&gt;
Net-Net, easy-way-out thing needs to go from our culture.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Average Indian is very very ignorant about what is going on in the world. Maybe so is the rest of world too, but hence the rest of world is not a superpower. &lt;strong&gt;To be a superpower, India needs to make information reach the last person.&lt;/strong&gt; There is a set of upcoming skill sets: green energy, AI, blockchain, Genetic Engineering and other things which will change the future. Also called forth industrial revolution, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2016/01/the-fourth-industrial-revolution-what-it-means-and-how-to-respond/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;The Fourth Industrial Revolution: what it means and how to respond&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;, we need to grow skills towards these new industries if we need to be a superpower. Indian students who will enter the labour market soon are wrongly advised and often end up studying for subjects which have literally very few opportunities in India. As a result , we have millions and millions of students who study for years in courses which they will not need. Think about how many millions of years we have wasted. So for handful of Civil Engineering jobs, where in India, one can just get in by a Polytechnic education ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuing_education&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Continuing education - Wikipedia&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;), we have students in almost all Engineering Colleges doing Civil Engineering majors. Why so ? A lot of them join jobs unrelated to their degree. We essentially convert degree workforce into secondary educated workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yes looking at points above, we need the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solve the information asymmetry.&lt;/strong&gt; Tell people what is the next big thing. Eventually people will understand, but we need to convert all the millions of years (mentioned earlier) we are wasting into good resources. This efficiency in economy will help us getting ahead fast. Government actually gets many surveys done, but it needs to let the information reach the masses the languages they can understand. Maybe something like a “Mann Ki Baat” for education and industry or Modi dedicating a few of these episodes to such topics ? (I will actually try suggesting this on their online suggestions portal).&lt;br /&gt;
Indians pay for Education. The recent wave of eductech startups might also solve this really well, but a more sober and serious voice than a young entrepreneur needs to convince the people that doing stupid majors is not worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make failing while trying to learn and do acceptable.&lt;/strong&gt; We have designed our incentives wrong way. Most of our people will find a person completing a PHD in 5 years with better publications worse than someone completing their PHD in 4 years with worse publications. We can &lt;strong&gt;maybe have research/entreprenurship courses in all degrees where we give marks for amount of hardwork done and not results.&lt;/strong&gt; It sounds easy, but Indians are master at avoiding hardwork as I told earlier, so needs to be done cleverly. In fact in a world where research is becoming very important (most industrial revolution 4 technologies need a graduate + level education) , we don’t have &lt;strong&gt;enough top tier people doing research&lt;/strong&gt; and its generally considered a career for those who want to do a “teaching” (not academic) job. This is a cultural thing and needs a collective resolve to move ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Government needs to stop giving useless scholarships in irrelevant subjects and direct this money into new sectors.&lt;/strong&gt; I heard recently that there is scholarship for studying (even research in these languages might not help the nation, but this scholarship is for doing a Bachelor degree, you need to pay like 3 cents a month as residential fees) Pashto and Persian in JNU. I don’t think that there is anyway this will help the country. We need to &lt;strong&gt;divert the money into STEM research, specifically AI.&lt;/strong&gt; Good resources flowing into AI research will definitely change the picture a lot. Think of economically weak students studying Computer Engineering on similar scholarships.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Force people out of their comfort zone:&lt;/strong&gt; This is not easy, but unless people are made to get out of their comfort zones, we wont get the efficiency required to become a post Industrial Revolution 4 superpower. Professors who are doing ineffective research need to be transitioned into a role where they can solve useful problems, companies need to attack more open-ended business problems to solve with AI and government needs to redirect investment from useless research and departments and PSUs to things that will yield good results in future. We need to make sure &lt;strong&gt;people are ready to get reeducated and reassigned and we need to then quickly change face of our economy.&lt;/strong&gt; This involves lot of uncertainties and people will need to adapt. As expected, it will be a hard pill to swallow, but better adapt before someone forces to adapt. Like point 2 this needs a collective resolve.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So , sum total, we need to develop a collective resolve to change the current situation. getting ahead in any field (including AI) needs resolve to change. Comfortable life if not something that will make you move ahead at a pace you can defeat others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-answer-to-where-does-india-stand-in-ai-5g-quantum-computing-biotech-and-clean-energy&quot;&gt;My Answer to “Where does India stand in AI, 5G, quantum computing, biotech, and clean energy?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally Answered Here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/pNncYq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is one of the leaders in &lt;strong&gt;Clean Energy&lt;/strong&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-04-14-Views-on-Indian-Startups/media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video URL Here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fyqDC_AKVgE&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://youtu.be/fyqDC_AKVgE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is also a quite advanced country in &lt;strong&gt;BioTech&lt;/strong&gt;, esp. Agriculture related :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;http://www.crri.nic.in/crri_sucstory.htm#Highprotine_rice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;CRRI-Success Stories&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/09/india-s-first-transgenic-food-crop-edges-toward-approval&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;India’s first transgenic food crop edges toward approval&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiwbr.org/achievements/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Achievements - ICAR- IIWBR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is the largest producer of vaccines in the world and its technology saves millions of lives :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehindu.com/sci-tech/health/trusting-the-science/article25861183.ece&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Trusting the science&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-04-14-Views-on-Indian-Startups/media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has its own &lt;strong&gt;Artificial Intelligence&lt;/strong&gt; startup scene as you might have read above&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with certain steps like ones mentioned earlier, we can ensure that India might even become an AI superpower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With government trying to bringing in some large scale projects, you can expect the AI capabilities to grow: &lt;a href=&quot;https://qr.ae/TeyvQH&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Muktabh Mayank’s answer to What do you think about India building the world’s largest face recognition system?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, being in top 10 is easy, being the best is really really hard in any of the fields I mentioned above. But India is giving a good fight I would say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quantum Computing&lt;/strong&gt; is still a very early stage technology and frankly I doubt a lot of “real” work is happening outside US, which is the innovation capital of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5G&lt;/strong&gt; is a lost cause, we have no companies that work in 5G technologies and all our telecom companies will be doing is paying huge sums of money to Chinese companies like Huawei to install these new cellphone networks. The technology will roll out soon in India, but it won’t be Indian technology as such.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Some Thoughts about Indian Startup Scene (As various answers to Quora questions)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Viewes On Fresher Data Science Jobs</title><link href="https://muktabh.xyz/2020/03/20/Viewes-on-Fresher-Data-Science-Jobs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Viewes On Fresher Data Science Jobs" /><published>2020-03-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-03-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://muktabh.xyz/2020/03/20/Viewes-on-Fresher-Data-Science-Jobs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muktabh.xyz/2020/03/20/Viewes-on-Fresher-Data-Science-Jobs.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;machine-learning-jobs-for-beginnersfreshers--my-perspective-from-various-quora-answers&quot;&gt;Machine Learning Jobs for beginners/freshers : My Perspective from various Quora Answers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will collect some of my answers here regarding fresher Machine Learrning jobs in India as I have some experience in this domain and hire in this domain quite often&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-should-i-do-to-get-a-job-in-machine-learning-in-india-&quot;&gt;Q. What should I do to get a job in Machine Learning in India ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a simple rule, work on an interesting project, get some results and put on display (Google, kaggle etc). Most employers can gauge your interest when they look at your profile. An entry level Machine Learning Engineer who can explain the Maths behind the algorithms they apply in some non-trivial problem is good enough for a lot of companies, they are not expecting seasoned veterans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following types of projects look very impressive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Taking a research/kaggle competition and working on its dataset. The code to handle such problems is a good proof of ones capability. The other good way is contributions to open source ML. The more you know what works behind your solution, the better.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Taking a paper (or taking a set of papers by a research group) and trying to code the algorithm/replicate the results is even better than 1 (at least for us at ParallelDots).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;An academic/industrial publication is even better.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is what is not enough:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Forking code for Bicycle challenge or other such competitions (the Titanic one as well) and running it and submitting that as previous work. They are too many tutorials for them and people won’t take you seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Completing Andrew Ng course.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Unless you are applying in a very big enterprise, I will say avoid certification and try working on personal projects. That is way more impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Again, Please don’t just fork code on Github and expect employers to believe you have worked. Its easy to see how much you have worked. :(&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HTH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer is here: https://www.quora.com/What-should-I-do-next-for-getting-a-job-in-Data-Science-and-Machine-Learning-in-India/answer/Muktabh-Mayank?srid=qie&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-is-it-not-possible-for-a-fresher-to-work-as-a-machine-learning-engineer-&quot;&gt;Q. Is it not possible for a fresher to work as a Machine Learning Engineer ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not “not possible” for a fresher to join as machine learning engineer if he she is very good at it. Wrong conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen freshers taking role of machine learning engineer at enterprises and even my startup. The problem is “he she is very good at it” part . Freshers often (not always, I know freshers with CVs as good as a professional ML engineer) over estimate their CVs as they don’t know about how real world works , they have very high expectations due to that and real world is unable to meet that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer is here: https://www.quora.com/Why-is-it-almost-impossible-for-a-fresher-to-join-as-a-ML-engineer-even-though-he-is-very-good-at-it/answer/Muktabh-Mayank?srid=qie&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-is-the-learning-path-after-going-through-basic-machine-leaning-material-&quot;&gt;Q. What is the learning path after going through basic Machine Leaning material ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Does one do projects, go for a summer training in Hadoop in Delhi, read books ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Please see link to blog posts below to find all these books)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IMHO, projects are the best way to learn (as you said you want to become a factory data scientist and are not in a mood to pursue a higher degree ). Taking different datasets for different types of problems and trying to come up with a data processing pipeline and then applying Machine Learning algorithms on top of it helped to clear many concepts for me. Its way more fun than all theory. Look at UCI or Kaggle datasets to apply your skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. From where should I do summer training in big data hadoop(Delhi)? (or in any other specific technology)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dont. Hadoop is just a framework to write programs. If from starting years of your career, you start concentrating on technologies (hadoop / mysql / postgre / java / python / scala and stuff like that), you will end up becoming a &amp;lt;specific technology&amp;gt; professional (say hadoop professional). Technology trends come and go, unless the fundamentals (which here is distributed computing) behind them is clear, one would never be able to adapt to the changing market . As long as you know programming basics well, stuff like Hadoop would be easy to pick up when your job requires it. You can try triggering a mapreduce job on your local system with help of an online tutorial, that is a different thing, but taking a full on course on hadoop is neither required nor recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some other points I would like to specify as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) Hadoop is for handling very large amount of data (Terabyte+), which most places do not have. Unlike what the internet hype (and plethora of hadoop training institutes in India want you to believe), most companies still have small data which can fit easily on a postgres cluster if not one server. Data Analysis skill is required almost everywhere, Hadoop at best in few 100 offices in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) Apart from HDFS, most parts of hadoop ecosystem are already being replaced/renovated by the innovation leader companies. Google (the inventor) phased out mapreduce &lt;a href=&quot;http://the-paper-trail.org/blog/the-elephant-was-a-trojan-horse-on-the-death-of-map-reduce-at-google/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;The Elephant was a Trojan Horse: On the Death of Map-Reduce at Google&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, projects like mahout already seem to be moving away from hadoop and a lot of companies seem to be moving towards &lt;a href=&quot;https://spark.apache.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Apache Spark™ - Lightning-Fast Cluster Computing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; . Now by the time you become professional, spark might be the talk of the town, in 10 more years even it might be removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would rather advice you to read books like mmds, foundations of data science, ISLR, Deep Learning etc. All of them are freely available on internet. Save your money and time (reading them now than you would read them after you graduate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edit : Adding the link to books (will rather link the blog post at ParallelDots we made collecting links to all these books, most of them freely available)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.paralleldots.com/data-science/24-best-and-free-books-to-understand-machine-learning/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Free Machine Learning Books&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.paralleldots.com/data-science/50-must-read-free-books-for-every-data-science-enthusiast/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Free Data Science Books&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.paralleldots.com/data-science/deep-learning/free-resources-deep-learning/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Free Deep Learning Resources&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.paralleldots.com/technology/artificial-intelligence/must-read-blogs-ai-deep-learning-enthusiasts/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Must Follow Blogs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer is Here: https://www.quora.com/What-should-be-the-learning-path-after-going-through-basic-machine-learning-material/answer/Muktabh-Mayank?srid=qie&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-do-companies-hire-data-scientists-with-zero-internship-experience&quot;&gt;Q. Do companies hire data scientists with zero internship experience?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. Doing an internship is not necessary to work in Data Science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most companies won’t hire Data Scientists with no experience of solving real world problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say anything out the following gives you equal (or more) weightage than internship at a tech startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A bronze medal or better at Kaggle,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A research project under an academic that resulted in a publication at a decent venue,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;An internship doing a proper AI project (which is to be deployed within the company), (whose alternatives we are discussing),&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Contribution to an open source project,&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Some other way in which you have worked in a real world setting optimizing for different constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger companies working in Data Science, maybe like Fractal and Manthan, might be hiring absolute freshers too, but most companies in this space are small startups who cannot take risk if hiring absolute freshers and training them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Original Answer Link: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/pNnch5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-is-it-true-that-maths-or-statistics-isnt-required-at-all-in-data-science-while-programming-skills-are-required-my-friend-told-me-the-same-thing-he-said-thats-why-a-majority-of-data-scientists-are-from-btech-backgrounds-not-from-maths-or-stats&quot;&gt;Q. Is it true that maths or statistics isn’t required at all in data science while programming skills are required? My friend told me the same thing. He said that’s why a majority of data scientists are from BTech backgrounds, not from maths or stats.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any respectable Engineering program (BTech) has a sizable number of Maths and Statistics courses. At BITS Pilani, I had coursework in Vector Calculus, Statistics, Linear Algebra, Differential Equations, Optimization and Operations Research (each one was a separate 1 semester long course) which every Engineering student had to take. On top of this there were Computer Science specific subjects (Data Mining, Machine Learning) which taught the Maths and Programming part both to everyone. The theory taught in these many courses is frankly enough to read most Data Science papers and understand concepts (You might need to read a couple of tutorials here and there).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the hypothesis that Engineering students aren’t aware of Maths and Stats is a wrong one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now about Data Scientists not needing Maths skill, data scientist as a job description is very broad just like software development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can say that Software Engineer doesn’t need to know about Databases, and that will be true for many people: Software Engineers who write Operating Systems, Software Engineers who develop frontend applications, Software Engineers who write compilers and below par Software Engineers who work on web application backends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are similarly many job descriptions for Data Scientists. Some of them actually don’t require too much Maths and just programming, but most of them do require some basics of the above mentioned mathematical areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Original Answer Here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/pNnctE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-my-answer-to-what-are-the-mistakes-people-make-when-they-start-machine-learning&quot;&gt;Q. My answer to “What are the mistakes people make when they start Machine Learning?”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally Answered here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/TiNJou&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some mistakes according to me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Focusing too much on math in the initial stages. To train your first Neural networks, you don’t need to know in detail how backprop works (backprop derivatives of all ops for example), or you don’t need to understand the support vector derivation to train SVMs. Dont start reading complicated mathematical resources in the beginning, it makes learning very slow. Touch on these topics when you are somewhat experienced writing code and training algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Focusing too little on Math is similarly bad too. Not knowing what different parameters to a Conv layer in Keras signify is also sub optimal. A basic book on Machine Learning with theory is best starting point.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Practising less. This is what differentiates between good and excellent practitioners. Most excellent practitioners can think of 100s of ideas around a dataset and can iterate quickly on them. That is how accuracy on a dataset will go up. Other practitioners will waste time in thinking about what would be the perfect method and code their “one best” method in hours, which will mostly not work in the end. You cannot think in advance what should be the method for best accuracy, EDA and trail-and-error is the key. Remember during practicing “Getting average accuracy on multiple datasets &amp;lt;&amp;lt; multiple round of iteration to get good accuracy on one dataset”.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Not focusing on basics numpy and pandas. As I said earlier, you need to iterate over many ideas quickly rather than thinking of “one true idea” that will work. Its grit boring work. To make this quicker, good command on Numpy and Pandas help. Lesser number of Google searhes == more code. Tensorflow/PyTorch have been purposefully written close to Numpy to make sure that Numpy users can iterate quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-are-some-signs-to-recognize-inexperienced-machine-learning-engineers-&quot;&gt;Q. What are some signs to recognize inexperienced Machine learning engineers ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Original Answer Here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/pNncvm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view most inexperienced Machine Learning people (including me say 6–7 years back) focus more on algorithm than data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newbies want to try out all the 250 (dummy number) algorithms on the dataset they have got without EDA on the data itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing the algorithm will generally give what 2–3% (again dummy number for giving an idea about magnitude) gains in accuracy, while, arranging/ balancing/ feature engineering/ augmenting the data can give manifold accuracy gains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine Learning is not yet a cool art where you summon a Charlizard and then it will be burn the competitor to the ground. It requires grit, getting dirty with the data and understanding what is the algorithm learning through many boring iterations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-i-just-hired-an-unqualified-machine-learning-engineer-he-know-only-some-basic-tensorflow-and-have-no-idea-about-the-maths-and-build-more-complex-neural-networks-should-i-fire-him-immediately-or-give-him-2-months-to-improve&quot;&gt;Q. I just hired an unqualified machine learning engineer, he know only some basic Tensorflow and have no idea about the maths and build more complex neural networks, should I fire him immediately or give him 2 months to improve?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally Answered Here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://qr.ae/pNncrn&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/pNncrn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did you hire an “unqualified” person ? Don’t you have a job description and interview process ? If there is such a huge gap between the hiring and requirement, I think its a problem with the company leadership and process. You should understand who you want to hire for what exact profile before you even put the JD out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you should do next is dependent on what is expected of the employee in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you expect him to do something Math(y) ? I don’t think they will be able to learn in 2 months. OTOH, 99.9% of the companies won’t need people who can write “new and complex” neural networks. Its mostly about transforming the data well, using clever training methods and loss functions etc. That said, even to gain enough experience for this, they will need more than 2 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general observation I have is that a lot of companies don’t have clear specs and requirements and they expect their Data Scientists to weave magic. Then they won’t hire senior people who can tell what is possible and what is not and put the entire pressure of expectations on cheap “fresher” employees, who generally have no real world experience (and many times will overestimate their capabilities, thus signing into something they cannot accomplish). This type of org structure is a house of cards. Hope this is not the case with your organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the work is running different open source models and experiments, 2 months is a decent time to learn and apply. If your expectation is in a domain , which is well worked and researched in, 2 months should be a good time for a less experienced person to catch up. If the expected work is this much, the hiring strategy is also not wrong and this is the general capability of talent available in the market. Groom them a bit for 2 months and everything should work out. If the expectation is any more open ended, you have made a wrong hiring decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-will-the-talent-shortage-in-ai-end-soon&quot;&gt;Q. Will the talent shortage in AI end soon?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally Answered Here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://qr.ae/TSkAzo&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/TSkAzo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of AI talent as of 2019 end. Too many people in India know basics about AI and can be trained to work. I am not sure if there is a way to see people applying for AI positions but if there was a way, you could clearly see that way many people apply for all AI/Data Science job (at least here in India). There was a time when just knowing some basics got you a job but no more now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem has now shifted to retaining top talent as too many people in the world are applying AI and working abroad is a big deal for most Indians. &lt;em&gt;So the situation is a lot more like Software Development profiles now for most AI profiles too.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a huge pool of talent and there is arms race for retaining top talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-will-data-science-and-machine-learning-get-automated-leading-to-lesser-opportunities-for-data-scientists-by-2025-&quot;&gt;Q. Will data science and machine learning get automated leading to lesser opportunities for data scientists by 2025 ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post is also an answer by me on Quora &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/Will-data-science-and-machine-learning-get-automated-leading-to-lesser-opportunities-for-data-scientists-as-per-https-www-datasciencecentral-com-profiles-blogs-data-scientists-automated-and-unemployed-by-2025-update/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;here&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. (2025 is not the date I think its going to happen, but its inevitable and will happen in near future). They will be automated to a good extent. So will be Software Developers, designers, manual workers, teachers, linguists, musicians, game developers etc,etc. There are already rudimentary projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.floydhub.com/turning-design-mockups-into-code-with-deep-learning/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Turning Design Mockups Into Code With Deep Learning&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which can turn a design mockup into HTML/CSS code, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/carpedm20/ENAS-pytorch&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;carpedm20/ENAS-pytorch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which can design neural networks without a Data Scientist, &lt;a href=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Why AutoML Is Set To Become The Future Of Artificial Intelligence&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , system which can generate new characters for games, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.business-standard.com/article/international/microsoft-ai-can-translate-chinese-to-english-just-as-accurately-as-humans-118031500414_1.html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Microsoft AI can translate Chinese to English just as accurately as humans&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.computing.co.uk/ctg/news/3028065/baidus-deep-voice-can-clone-speech-with-less-than-four-seconds-of-training&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Baidu’s Deep Voice can clone speech with less than four seconds of training | Computing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and multiple such projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-03-20-Viewes-on-Fresher-Data-Science-Jobs/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video Link : &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://youtu.be/XOxxPcy5Gr4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI will impact every job profile which exists as of now, Data Scientists no exception, automating some or a lot of work people spend their time on. For a lot of time these systems will become a &amp;lt;Man + Machine&amp;gt; AI systems rather than just a Human working before stuff is totally automated. So its not like everyone becomes redundant day 1, but they will eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full Automation of any field is going to take way longer than 2025 IMHO. That said, yes a lot less people will be needed for the same task as of today. Then what will people do you ask ? newer more complex tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automation is not a new phenomenon. Think about the railway breaks a long time back:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-03-20-Viewes-on-Fresher-Data-Science-Jobs/media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video Link Here: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://youtu.be/EEUkmP2nyxo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much work was once needed to just stop the train. A lot lesser work is needed today to run/stop the train and not just that, slowly trains are moving towards full automation, but right now they are in a &amp;lt;man + machine&amp;gt; stage. A lot of jobs will stay in this phase for sometime before full automation kicks in. But unlike railways, which take generations to move from one stage of automation to another, AI is causing changes at a very high rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the effect on a general Data Scientist (or any white/blue collared worker for that matter):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Adapt to AI. Automation has started, but AI aided jobs will stay for a few more years than non-AI jobs. So while no plain X jobs by 2025, X + AI jobs might be around till 2030.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Things wont be like earlier generations where one skill learnt gets you a job for entire life. One needs to be open to learning new skills and get started in the middle of life.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Average level of education needed will be high. Think of it, 50 years back “High School” was all the education needed for most jobs. Now its somewhere between high school and graduation. Masters and Research might look like the next frontier, but these degrees are too slow and broad. Coursera like courses will become more important in catching new skillsets. You might already see people doing that a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;With more uncertainty in jobs, millenials probably will want to be a less “spend-y” and more frugal. You can see things happening already &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.in/6-reasons-why-more-millennials-arent-buying-homes/articleshow/59005530.cms&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;6 reasons why more millennials aren’t buying homes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and will actually increase. AI is just a trend in a longer cycle of Automation and millenials are at a point in history where education+society was according to old norms but automation has reached a point where jobs have become uncertain. Younger people will be smarter.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;h3 id=&quot;q-why-are-kaggle-grandmasters-in-a-great-demand&quot;&gt;Q. Why are Kaggle Grandmasters in a great demand?&lt;/h3&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because they work really really hard on Applied Machine Learning (that’s what kaggle is) and thus have become really good at their job. If there is a hard Machine Learning problem with Billion dollars behind it, with a high probability, Kaggle grandmasters will be able to solve it better than an average joe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working consistently on something for years makes one a master of the art. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outliers_\(book\)&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Outliers (book) - Wikipedia&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-03-20-Viewes-on-Fresher-Data-Science-Jobs/media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People really good at their job (say in top 10%) are really sought after in any field, not just Machine Learning. They drive the innovation, solve open ended problems and hence they get the rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-03-20-Viewes-on-Fresher-Data-Science-Jobs/media/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-how-do-i-become-a-data-scientist-in-2020-in-india-by-self-teaching&quot;&gt;Q. How do I become a data scientist in 2020 in India by self-teaching?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally answered the question on Quora here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://qr.ae/TmYc20&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://qr.ae/TmYc20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think the path to being Data Scientist in India is different from being a Data Scientist abroad. It is in fact 99% same if you live in a place with good internet connectivity and understand English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to clarify to yourself the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;1. As a self-learner, determine if you like learning from books or like learning in virtual classrooms.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;2. Either way, you will have to dedicate around 10000 hours of hard work to learning and practical exercises. It looks simple, but most people lose out here. They do not put enough effort.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;3. Point 2 above requires self drive. It is not easy. A proxy to that is buying online courses / books. The money you put into them makes you (and probably your parents who drive most people towards learning stuff) have skin-in-the-game and you wont want to lose out. If you arent that wealthy, you will have to push yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;4. You have to invest in a good computer. (somewhat 60000 INR cost).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;5. You need to have good internet.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is all. There are enough resources available for free to learn and make yourself a good data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;1. Learn Python programming. This is first and foremost. There are many free books and online courses to learn Python (sometimes Python for Data Science specifically) if you aren’t enrolling in a course. When you are doing a course or reading a book, don’t just read it, force yourself into using python after you are done learning. If book exercises look boring to you, join a startup near you as a free intern and do some coding for them. Forcing yourself to write 1000 lines of code (made up number) is very important.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;2. Make yourself comfortable with Python ecosystem : Numpy, Scikit_learn, Keras, PyTorch, Pandas. There are courses and free books available to do these. Look for their ratings on goodreads (for books) and course stars. Best is to just do the famous courses &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/specializations/data-science-python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Applied Data Science with Python | Coursera&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;http://deeplearning.ai/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;http://deeplearning.ai&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/machine-learning&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Machine Learning | Coursera&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; . If you are looking for free books, check out some lists I curated on ParallelDots blog: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.paralleldots.com/data-science/50-must-read-free-books-for-every-data-science-enthusiast/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://blog.paralleldots.com/data-science/50-must-read-free-books-for-every-data-science-enthusiast/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.paralleldots.com/data-science/24-best-and-free-books-to-understand-machine-learning/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://blog.paralleldots.com/data-science/24-best-and-free-books-to-understand-machine-learning/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.paralleldots.com/data-science/deep-learning/free-resources-deep-learning/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://blog.paralleldots.com/data-science/deep-learning/free-resources-deep-learning/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.paralleldots.com/data-science/nlp/free-natural-language-processing-resources/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://blog.paralleldots.com/data-science/nlp/free-natural-language-processing-resources/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; . Force yourself to write more and more code. Do problem sets from courses, exercises from books, work for free in a startup, enter analyticsvidhya competitions or whatever suits you. Unless you practice after you learn, its not going to work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;3. This much will make you employable by many companies. If you still are trying to push to learn more, you will have to start reading research literature. This is not entirely necessary, but if you still want to, you should get yourself associated with some decent university group (or a research startup), where novel problem statements are being solved. This step is really hard without talking to peers, but if you are really self driven, Twitter is a good place to follow people and handles to learn about research while being outside the research world. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@andreas_madsen/becoming-an-independent-researcher-and-getting-published-in-iclr-with-spotlight-c93ef0b39b8b&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Becoming an Independent Researcher and getting published in ICLR with spotlight&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Machine Learning Jobs for beginners/freshers : My Perspective from various Quora Answers</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Views On Coronavirus</title><link href="https://muktabh.xyz/2020/02/27/Views-on-Coronavirus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Views On Coronavirus" /><published>2020-02-27T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-02-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://muktabh.xyz/2020/02/27/Views-on-Coronavirus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muktabh.xyz/2020/02/27/Views-on-Coronavirus.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-we-know-about-coronavirus--what-to-do-and-what-not-to-&quot;&gt;What we know about CoronaVirus ? What to do and what not to ?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to write this as new cases of CoronaVirus have come up in India in early March 2020. I thus want to make as much information publicly (and easily) available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, we don’t know a lot about the virus ! For Science, answers to a lot of questions are “We don’t know”. With the bombardment of facts and opinions coming to you through social media, you should understand what is True and what is a guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-coronavirus-and-where-does-it-come-from-&quot;&gt;What is CoronaVirus and where does it come from ?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus is a very common species of virus. It is found in different animals and generally doesn’t effect humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However the nCov (novel Coronavirus) is a particular type of coronavirus which causes COVID19 disease. The disease that is wreaking a havoc in China, South Korea, Italy ands Iran and many people have already died. COVID19 can cause Flu-like symptoms and can grow to severe pneumonia or organ failure causing deaths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://www.statnews.com/2020/02/14/disease-modelers-see-future-of-covid-19/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble with COVID19 is that while it is very contagious like the common flu, it is really deadly. (A preprint from a Chinese study centre says it kills upto 4% of the people it infects). A lot more people will experience severe symptoms when they contract the disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cite: &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.02.10.20021675v2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other studies that show morality rate to be between 1%-2% as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coronavirus which causes COVID19 was not around until a few days back. It is a mixture of two different Coronavirus strains from two different animals. Bats have a unique type of immune system (ie, it is always working at full capacity to defect against viruses), so the virus which have evolved to attack bats are really fast to spread so that they can overwhelm the immune system. When such viruses evolve to attack humans, they become very deadly as unlike bats, human immune system triggers after it is sure of an infection. This viruses thus find it relatively easier to overwhelm human immune system than in bats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bats have been source of many different viruses that have effected humans in recent years. SARS (last decade in China), Ebola (few years back in Liberia and surrounding countries in Africa), Nipah virus (few years back in India) all came from bats. With humans intruding into natural habitats (forests) of bats, the frequency of encounters is bound to go up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://phys.org/news/2020-02-coronavirus-outbreak-viruses-deadly.html&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes the matter even worst is the consumption of wild animals as meat in some areas of the world. This leads to unregulated sales of wild animal meat in open markets. In Africa’s Ebola outbreak, bushmeat consumption is what causes the Ebola virus to evolve into the deadly thing it became. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/importation/bushmeat.html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Bushmeat Importation Policies | CDC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In China, wet markets , or markets where exotic animals and seafood are kept together and killed for human consumption are supposed to be the cause of Coronavirus outbreak. The bat coronavirus is not able to infect humans directly. However, there was a transfer of the virus from bats to most probably pangolins when they were kept together or their body fluids got mixed before they became capable enough to attack humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://medicalxpress.com/news/2020-02-pangolin-potential-link-coronavirus.html&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://phys.org/news/2020-02-illegally-trafficked-pangolins-link-coronavirus.html&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it seems that the Pangolin discovery was an incorrect one. All we know is Bat Coronavirus merged with another strain and became nCov we know today. So we don’t yet fully know how the virus originated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-00548-w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image6.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SARS, another Coronavirus outbreak in the previous decade was caused due to human consumption of civets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember while the nCov originated in animals, it has the capability to spread from person to person. So don’t be under the assumption if you avoid animals you are not at risk. nCov somewhat spreads like common cold and flu.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, that we know where did the virus come from, we can now understand how it spreads. Coronavirus is slightly heavy as compared to the common cold virus, rhinovirus. So the probability of it being aerosolized as an infected person sneezes or coughs are slightly lower. And even if that happens, the virus will be able to travel less distance in air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, stand away from people showing symptoms like sneezing and coughing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, people can infect doorknobs, mobile screens, washroom faucets when they touch these objects. The virus can then be picked by other people when they use the objects upto a week after an infected person touches them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the virus reaches a new person’s hands, it will not get into by skin, but when they touch eyes, ears, nose or mouth with these hands without washing. If an infected person sneezes or coughs very close to an uninfected person’s face, water droplets can enter their eyes or mouth directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, wash your hands very very often with a disinfectant like Dettol etc. Also when in a supposedly infected area, cover your nose, mouth and eyes with a mask and glasses. When used, dispose these object cleverly and wash hands afterwards.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have also started inventing clever touch-less buttons etc. to avoid getting in touch of infected surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend CTT came up with a very interesting design for proximity sensing, no-contact elevator buttons- that still provide the satisfying visual movement of being pressed. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/fpUEs4mLQ8&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/fpUEs4mLQ8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;— Naomi Wu 机械妖姬 (@RealSexyCyborg) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RealSexyCyborg/status/1227454423699509254?ref_src=twsrc^tfw&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;February 12, 2020&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following section about growth was written in early February and in China the growth rate seems to have slowed down since then, however, outside China you can see a similar growth rate in Korea, Iran etc. :&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember, prevention is the only thing possible right now. There is no known cure as of 15th Feb. Many medicines are being given a trial and we might have one soon, in a few months, years or maybe never.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at NN Taleb’s predictions, the virus will spread like wildfire. Surprisingly, the virus has been following an exponential curve for sometime as expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image9.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image10.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, some tips :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Avoid crowds and travel unless absolutely necessary. This reduces the probability of you getting in contact with the virus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Keep some long shelf life products like rice, grams etc ready at home.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Try having a Water purification system that works without electricity too. You dont want to increase risk of other water borne infections.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Stock medicines for other conditions like fever etc and for hypertension, high BP, diabetes if someone has the conditions in your family.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Avoid shaking hands and try staying away from other crowds and unnecessary travelling. Going out in crowds increases your risk factor for contracting coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image11.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, this is way more serious than common flu unlike what many MSM outlets are saying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the answer has made you panic, here is some Simpsons (predicts future) humor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image12.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also , here is an Indian Newspaper reporting the humor as if it is real news:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/magazines/panache/the-simpsons-predicts-the-future-again-episode-cited-as-a-prophecy-of-the-coronavirus/articleshow/73949972.cms&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;‘The Simpsons’ predicts the future, again: Episode cited as a prophecy of the coronavirus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now for people who like reading specific answers, I will write answers for various FAQs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;q1-are-vegetarians-immune-to-covid19-&quot;&gt;Q1. Are vegetarians immune to COVID19 ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A1. COVID19 originated in wet markets selling meat, but it now has human to human transfer capacity like Common Cold and Flu. Staying away from animals reduces risk of coronavirus contraction, but there is no guarantee that no animal contact makes you safe. So no, vegetarians are not immune to COVID 19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;q2-are-masks-helpful-or-not-&quot;&gt;Q2. Are masks helpful or not ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A2. CoronaVirus is a heavier virus when compared to say common cold. So it cannot stay suspended in air for very long. This means that if you are standing away from an infected person (2 Meters +), there is a very low probability of virus contraction from air. So that means you do not need masks as long as you are in spaces where people aren’t too closeby to you. Only in places where infection is widespread (like hospitals) and in cases where you have to get too close to people infected with CoronaVirus, you should use a mask. Also please note using a mask is almost useless without using protective eye wear. When you use a mask, you should dispose it off well and wash your hands after removing the mask. Please note its better to avoid infected places and mass gatherings than using masks. Not only masks are not 100% effective, you also choke the supply for health workers who require these to take care of the sick. Please read the directions if you choose to wear masks : &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/advice-for-public/when-and-how-to-use-masks&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/advice-for-public/when-and-how-to-use-masks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; . Also remember to not buy and stockpile masks, this creates shortage and health workers need them much more than you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;q3-as-a-normal-person-what-is-the-most-effective-way-to-avoid-infection-&quot;&gt;Q3. As a normal person, what is the most effective way to avoid infection ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A3. Minimize going into public places. That is the most effective method and reduces the probability of you catching the infection by a lot. Keep washing your hands frequently using alcohol sanitizers or soap. It has been scientifically proven that it works quite well. Avoid touching your eyes, mouth or nose unnecessarily. If you feel a strong need to do so, clean your hands before doing so. The disease seems to be spreading through contaminated surfaces like door knobs, lift buttons, phone screens etc. Practice hand hygiene after touching any such possible surface. &lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/layallivs/status/1234849244709883905?s=08&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image13.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;q4-isnt-the-covid19-just-another-flu-&quot;&gt;Q4. Isn’t the COVID19 just another Flu ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A4. No, its not. COVID19 has a way higher fatality rate (best estimates around 1- 2%) and need for hospitalization rate than normal Flu from what we know. There is no comparison. For elderly people, the mortality rate can be as high as 1 in 3. You should make sure you dont act as a carrier for virus infecting elderly people. Luckily, for people younger than 20 years, COVID mortality rate is really less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;q5-it-doesnt-seem-to-be-as-deadly-as-say-ebola-why-so-much-worry-&quot;&gt;Q5. It doesn’t seem to be as deadly as say Ebola. Why so much worry ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A5. Because COVID19 follows textbook definition of Viral. If it starts spreading, it spreads at a rapid rate and 2% of a large number can be a very high number. For example, if allowed to spread unconstrained, it can spread to population as large as 40%-70% of the entire world. That’s over 3 Billion people. 2% of 3 Billion is 60 Million lives! That would be a terrible terrible loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;q6-does-the-virus-die-in-hothumid-temperatures-&quot;&gt;Q6. Does the virus die in hot/humid temperatures ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A6. Maybe. We don’t know for sure. It might be that the virus becomes inactive in hot and humid weather. That conclusion comes from that it has spread less in tropics than temperate/cold climate. But this might just be a co-incidence. As of 4&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; March 2020, you cannot be sure that the virus will not spread in your vicinity because of it being hot and humid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;q7-why-is-india-still-getting-an-increased-number-of-coronavirus-cases-per-day-if-they-are-locked-down-for-a-while&quot;&gt;Q7. Why is India still getting an increased number of coronavirus cases per day if they are locked down for a while?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is quite simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Most of the people as of now (24th March) tested positive for CoronaVirus are Indian and Foreign citizens who returned from abroad (the remaining ones are people who came in contact with this). While India stopped visas a long time back, its own citizens from abroad were thronging to our airports (its just two days back all international traffic was stopped). Our citizens continued entering just upto two days back. About 26000 people entered Mumbai from Dubai, we have no way to control infection amongst people who are arriving pre-infected here. &lt;a href=&quot;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/politics-and-nation/coronavirus-worst-hit-maharashtra-set-to-welcome-26000-gulf-returnees/articleshow/74706096.cms&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Coronavirus: Worst-hit Maharashtra set to welcome 26,000 Gulf returnees&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://muktabh.xyz/assets/img/2020-02-27-Views-on-Coronavirus/media/image14.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The number of Corona cases you see on Television is actually a snapshot of a few days to a few weeks back. Reason its is seen COVID19 doesn’t show symptoms immediately. It takes a few days to 2 weeks for symptoms to emerge and then people visit hospitals at different stages after the symptoms appear. They are spreading the virus all along. The lockdowns were imposed only a few days back.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The first few days of lockdown were voluntary and while majority of people followed them, there were a few people who did not take it seriously. While the rate would have definitly fallen (we would see good numbers in a few days to weeks), but now that absolute lockdowns are being ensured, it should get even better beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;h2 id=&quot;q8-if-a-person-has-had-the-coronavirus-are-they-more-or-less-likely-to-contract-it-a-second-time&quot;&gt;Q8. If a person has had the coronavirus, are they more or less likely to contract it a second time?&lt;/h2&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, we don’t know that yet. We have opinions but no definite conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CoronaVirus (not the recent one causing COVID19, but other more common types), along with RhinoVirus cause common cold and it seems the body doesn’t develop an immunity against that disease. You keep getting the cold every year, dont you ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologynetworks.com/immunology/news/why-dont-we-ever-develop-immunity-against-the-common-cold-294551&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Why Don’t We Ever Develop Immunity Against the Common Cold?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there are arguments like a certain portion of human population are innately immune against the COVID19 causing virus. If a few people can be immune, so can be all people with immunization/exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jpost.com/HEALTH-SCIENCE/Israeli-nobel-laureate-Coronavirus-spread-is-slowing-621145&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Coronavirus spread is slowing - Says Israeli Nobel Laureate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;q9-as-there-is-no-vaccine-for-coronavirus-how-are-people-being-cured-of-it&quot;&gt;Q9. As there is no vaccine for coronavirus, how are people being cured of it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Vaccines don’t cure you from viruses. Your immune system cures you by destroying cells infected by viruses. The aim of a vaccine is to somehow make sure that your immune system is already ready with a response for a virus we know humans aren’t innately immune to. This is done by delivering a harmless entity like weakened virus or a clue to recognize the virus (protein etc) into the body so that immune system learns to recognize and kill beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case of a novel virus (something never seen before), the body’s immune system has no clue about the virus and has to come up with a strategy to kill the virus while being infected. Novel-Coronavirus (SARS2 which causes COVID19) is a novel virus. Unlike a vaccine , where a body learns to fight the virus for free, here its a question of whether body can come up with a strategy to kill the virus before the virus does serious damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a lot of people (over 95%), their bodies are able to come up with methods to beat the Novel-CoronaVirus when they get infected. (It is not known whether the body develops long term immunity post getting better though) . For the others, the results might be really bad :( . Specially people who have weakened immune systems (people take drugs to weaken immune response in various diseases), diabetes, high BP or weak lungs/organs due to smoking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for people whose immunity cannot fight off COVID19 (or even whose immunity can fight it off), another way to stop the virus is antiviral drugs. These drugs (generally) stop production of various viral proteins reducing/stopping the growth of virus, thus reducing the work of immune system to kill the virus. There are a few antiviral treatments that might be working for COVID19. We still have very primary data about it, but people are already using these drugs as last resort:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hydroxy Choloroquin + Azithromycin seems to work in a trial in France. There have been other studies about Chloroquin derivatives in COVID19 outbreak as well as before it (during SARS outbreak in 2002). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0924857920300996&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin as a treatment of COVID-19: results of an open-label non-randomized clinical trial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Meplazumab has been tried in China and seems to work well : &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.03.21.20040691v1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Meplazumab treats COVID-19 pneumonia: an open-labelled, concurrent controlled add-on clinical trial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Japanese drug Favipiravir has been found to be successful in a trial of 340 patients as claimed by China. &lt;a href=&quot;https://nypost.com/2020/03/18/japanese-flu-drug-clearly-effective-in-treating-coronavirus-officials-say/&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;Japanese flu drug ‘clearly effective’ in treating coronavirus, officials say&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Remdesivir might be another drug that could be proven in future to cure off the virus: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2020/03/24/821035311/fda-grants-experimental-coronavirus-drug-benefits-for-rare-disease-treatments&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;underline&quot;&gt;FDA Grants Experimental Coronavirus Drug Benefits For Rare Disease Treatments&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;##&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;h2 id=&quot;q10-aside-from-a-pune-based-diagnostic-company-mylab-has-developed-the-first-made-in-india-test-kit-for-coronavirus-in-a-record-time-of-6-weeks-how-will-this-help-us-to-control-corona&quot;&gt;Q10. Aside from a Pune-based diagnostic company, myLab has developed the first made in India test kit for coronavirus in a record time of 6 weeks. How will this help us to control corona?&lt;/h2&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The more testing kits we have, more people we can test and isolate. Not just this, myLab kits also provide results fast. This helps stop spread by identifying all infected quickly by testing more suspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a hypothetical condition, if the entire 1.3 Billion people are tested and people who have the virus are isolated, and everyone entering country is given a coronavirus test, the others can go about doing day-to-day work as if nothing has happened as there will be no danger of infection. Until this is not achieved heavy quarantine will be needed (the more you can test and isolate, the lesser quarantine is needed like South Korea). Importing 1.3 Billion kits will probably cost a huge chunk of India’s GDP ! If we could build it in house cheaply, it would be pretty good, not 1 Billion, then say 100 Million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to make a model between China’s model and South Korea’s model. (that’s what government is doing)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What we know about CoronaVirus ? What to do and what not to ?</summary></entry></feed>